<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
        <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
        <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
        <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
        <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" category="bcp" obsoletes="7454" consensus="true" version="3" docName="draft-ietf-grow-bgpopsecupd-latest">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="BGP OPSEC">Updated BGP Operations and Security</title>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" status="standard" value="draft-ietf-grow-bgpopsecupd-latest"/>
        <author fullname="Tobias Fiebig" initials="T." surname="Fiebig">
            <organization abbrev="MPI-INF">Max-Planck-Institut fuer Informatik</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Campus E14</street>
                    <city>Saarbruecken</city>
                    <code>66123</code>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+49 681 9325 3527</phone>
                <email>tfiebig@mpi-inf.mpg.de</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Nick Hilliard" initials="N." surname="Hilliard">
            <organization abbrev="INEX">Internet Neutral Exchange Association</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>4027 Kingswood Road</street>
                    <city>Citywest, Dublin</city>
                    <code>D24 AX96</code>
                    <country>Ireland</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+353 1 433 205 2</phone>
                <email>nick@inex.ie</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <area>ops</area>
        <workgroup>Global Routing Operations</workgroup>

        <abstract>
            <t>
                The Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) is a critical component in the Internet to exchange routing information between network domains.
                Due to this central nature, it is important to understand the security and reliability requirements that can and should be ensured to prevent accidental or intentional routing disturbances.
            </t>
            <t>
                Previously, security considerations for BGP have been described in RFC7454 / BCP194.
                Since the publications of RFC7454 / BCP194, several developments and changes in operational practice took place that warrant an update of these best current practices.
                This document replaces RFC7454 / BCP194, focusing on the overall goals, and providing a less implementation centric set of best practices.
            </t>
            <t>
                To this end, the document describes the security requirements and goals when operating BGP for exchanging routing information with other networks.
                The document explicitly does not focus on specific technical implementations and requirements.
                Operators are advised to consult documentation and contemporary informational documents concerning methods to ensure that these properties are sufficiently ensured in their network.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section  anchor="sec-introduction">
            <name>Introduction</name>
            <t>
                The Border Gateway Protocol (BGP), specified in <xref target="RFC4271" format="default"/>, is the protocol used in the Internet to exchange routing information between network domains.
                BGP does not directly include mechanisms that control whether the routes exchanged conform to the various guidelines defined by the Internet community.
                Furthermore, the BGP protocol itself, by its design, does not have any direct way to protect itself against threats to confidentiality, integrity, and availability.
                This document summarizes security properties and requirements when operating BGP for securing the infrastructure as well as for security considerations regarding the exchanged routing information.
            </t>
            <section>
                <name>Requirements Language</name>
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                  "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
                  RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
                  interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
                  <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
                  all capitals, as shown here.</t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section  anchor="sec-scope-of-the-document">
            <name>Scope of the Document</name>
            <t>
                The guidelines defined in this document are intended for BGP when used to exchange generic Internet routing information within the DFZ.
                It specifically does not cover other uses of BGP, e.g., when using BGP for NLRI exchange in a data-center context.
                This document does not specify how the outlined requirements and properties can be technically realized at a specific point in time.
                Instead, operators are advised to consult applicable documentation and contemporary informational documents describing implementation specifics.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section  anchor="sec-protection-of-the-bgp-speaker">
            <name>Protection of the BGP Speaker and Session</name>

            <t>
                The BGP speaker, i.e., the host running BGP to exchange routing information, needs to be protected from external attempts to taint integrity or availability of the BGP session and host alike.
            </t>

            <section  anchor="sec-protection-of-the-bgp-speaker-net">
                <name>BGP Session Protection</name>
                <t>
                    To protect a BGP speaker on the network layer, an operator <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure the following properties using technical or organizational measures:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                    <li>
                        Prevent off-path attackers from injecting BGP messages into existing sessions.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Prevent off-path attackers from interrupting existing sessions.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Prevent off-path attackers from preventing the establishment of new sessions.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Prevent remote systems from overwhelming the BGP speaker by sending large volumes of unsolicited packets or BGP messages.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Ensure that unstable sessions do not threaten the availability of BGP speakers within the network.
                    </li>
                </ul>

            </section>

            <section  anchor="sec-protection-of-the-bgp-speaker-mgmt">
                <name>BGP Speaker Management Interface Protection</name>

                <t>
                    In addition to the control plane / exchange of BGP protocol messages, the management plane of BGP speakers must be appropriately secured.
                    Hence, operators <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure that:
                </t>

                <ul spacing="normal">
                    <li>
                        No unauthorized third-parties can obtain access or connect to the management interface of a BGP speaker in a way that allows tainting confidentiality, integrity, or availability.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        External activity towards the management interface do not interfere with the integrity or availability of BGP sessions.
                    </li>
                </ul>

            </section>

        </section>
        <section  anchor="sec-nlri-filtering">
            <name>NLRI Filtering</name>
            <t>
                The purpose of BGP is exchanging routing information, i.e., NLRI.
                Importing or exporting incorrect or malicious NLRI is a security risk for networks themselves, but may also form a threat for connected and/or remote networks.
                As such, operators <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure the following properties when importing or exporting routing information from their neighbors.
            </t>
            <section  anchor="sec-importing-nlri">
                <name>Importing NLRI</name>
                <t>
                    When importing NLRI from a neighbor, an operator <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure that all imported NLRI conform to the following properties by implementing technical or organizational measures:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                    <li>
                        The AS originating NLRI for a prefix <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be globally authorized to originate that prefix. Operators <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> deviate from this for default routes (::/0 and 0.0.0.0/0), if they granted the specific neighbor permission to announce default routes towards them.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The AS_PATH of the NLRI <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> violate the valley-free principle <xref target="RFC4012" format="default"/>, i.e., all ASes left of the originating AS in the AS_PATH <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be authorized to advertise the NLRI to the AS directly to their left.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The AS_PATH <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain AS numbers reserved for private <xref target="RFC6996" format="default"/> or special-use cases not necessitating their presence in the global routing table <xref target="IANAASNSpec" format="default"/>.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The number of NLRI received from a neighbor <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> exceed the resources of the local router.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </section>
            <section  anchor="sec-exporting-nlri">
                <name>Originating and Redistributing NLRI</name>
                <t>
                    When originating NLRI or redistributing NLRI received from a neighbor, an operator <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure that all NLRI they export conform to the following properties by implementing technical or organizational measures:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                    <li>
                        The AS_PATH of redistributed NLRI <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> violate the valley-free principle <xref target="RFC4012" format="default"/>, i.e., the redistributing AS <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be authorized to redistribute NLRI for the specific prefix when received from the AS directly to its right in the AS_PATH. Additionally, each AS in the AS_PATH not originating the prefix <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be authorized to redistribute the prefix when receiving it from the next AS to its right.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The AS originating NLRI for a prefix <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be globally authorized to originate that prefix. Operators <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> deviate from this for default routes (::/0 and 0.0.0.0/0), if they originate the default route and the specific neighbor granted them permission to announce default routes towards them.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The AS_PATH <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain AS numbers reserved for private <xref target="RFC6996" format="default"/> or special-use cases not necessitating their presence in the global routing table <xref target="IANAASNSpec" format="default"/>.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </section>
            <section  anchor="sec-handling-nlri">
                <name>General Considerations for Altering NLRI</name>
                <t>
                    When processing NLRI, an operator <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure that some basic properties of these NLRI are not altered or set:
                </t>
                <ul spacing="normal">
                    <li>
                        An operator <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> change transitive BGP attributes, if the attribute is unknown to the operator. In selected cases, if a specific attribute is known to be malicious, an operator <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> filter that specific attribute or the NLRI.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        NLRI carried on BGP <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be enriched with transitive attributes subject to change independent of the underlying NLRI, e.g., encoding RPKI validation state in transitive attributes <xref target="I-D.spaghetti-sidrops-avoid-rpki-state-in-bgp" format="default"/>.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section  anchor="sec-iana-considerations">
            <name>IANA Considerations</name>
            <t>
                This document does not require any IANA actions.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section  anchor="sec-security-considerations">
            <name>Security Considerations</name>
            <t>
                This document is entirely about BGP operational security.
                It lists requirements and properties operators <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure using technical or organizational measures when operating BGP routers in the DFZ.
            </t>
            <t>
                However, it does not detail how the outlined properties and security requirements can be implemented and enforced in practice.
                This is a conscious choice given that available techniques and methods to ensure these properties will change over time, while the underlying principles remain the same.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references>
            <name>References</name>
            <references>
                <name>Normative References</name>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6996.xml"/>
                <reference anchor="I-D.spaghetti-sidrops-avoid-rpki-state-in-bgp" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-spaghetti-sidrops-avoid-rpki-state-in-bgp/">
                    <front>
                        <title>Guidance to Avoid Carrying RPKI Validation States in Transitive BGP Path Attributes</title>
                        <author initials="J." surname="Snijders" fullname="Job Snijders">
                            <organization>Fastly</organization>
                        </author>
                        <author initials="T." surname="Fiebig" fullname="Tobias Fiebig">
                            <organization>MPI-INF</organization>
                        </author>
                        <author initials="M. A." surname="Stucchi" fullname="Massimiliano Stucchi">
                            <organization>AS58280.net</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date month="February" day="8" year="2024"/>
                    </front>
                    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-spaghetti-sidrops-avoid-rpki-state-in-bgp-00"/>
                </reference>
                <reference anchor="IANAASNSpec" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/iana-as-numbers-special-registry/iana-as-numbers-special-registry.xhtml">
                  <front>
                    <title>Special-Purpose Autonomous System (AS) Numbers</title>
                    <author>
                      <organization>IANA</organization>
                    </author>
                  </front>
                </reference>
            </references>
            <references>
                <name>Informative References</name>

                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4012.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7454.xml"/>
            </references>
        </references>
        <section anchor="acknowledgements" numbered="false" toc="default">
            <name>Acknowledgements</name>
            <t>
                This document has been originally based on <xref target="RFC7454" format="default"/> and we thank the original authors for their work.
            </t>
            <t>
                We thank the following people for reviewing this draft and suggesting changes:
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
                <li>
                    Gert Doerring
                </li>
                <li>
                    Jeff Haas
                </li>
                <li>
                    Geng Nan
                </li>
                <li>
                    Martin Pels
                </li>
                <li>
                    Job Snijders
                </li>
                <li>
                    Berislav Todorovic
                </li>
                <li>
                    Martin Pels
                </li>
                <li>
                    Wolfgang Tremmel
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
